CARMEN S. CHUI Ph.D. Candidate

5 King's College Road, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON M5S 3G8 CANADA

SUMMARY

I am a final year Ph.D. candidate specializing in knowledge representation and modelling, as well as the design and analysis of first-order ontologies. My current research involves the design of a molecular structure ontology for medicinal chemistry in first-order logic, as well as providing model construction techniques for drug discovery. I hope to acquire research, teaching, and working experience in an environment where my skills and educational foundation can be further developed.

RESEARCH INTERESTS

- Ontology design, mapping, integration, and verification
- Knowledge representation & modelling
- · Automated reasoning of first-order ontologies
- Applications of ontologies to data and knowledge integration
- Engineering education

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Industrial Engineering

09/2013-present

University of Toronto

♥ Toronto, Canada

- Dissertation: "A Molecular Structure Ontology for Medicinal Chemistry"
- Adviser: Michael Grüninger
- Committee: Mark Fox, Michael Grüninger, L.H. Shu
- Completed the Prospective Professors in Training (PPIT) Program in 2018

M.A.Sc. in Industrial Engineering

09/2011-08/2013

University of Toronto

♥ Toronto, Canada

- Dissertation: "Axiomatized Relationships Between Ontologies"
- Adviser: Michael Grüninger
- Committee: Mark Fox, Michael Grüninger, L.H. Shu
- Received Teaching Fundamentals (TF) Certificate from the Teaching Assistants' Training Program (TATP) in 2012

B.A.Sc. (with honours) in Industrial Engineering

09/2007-06/2011

University of Toronto

▼ Toronto, Canada

- Information Systems option stream
- Fourth year research thesis: "Reasoning About Changes"

PUBLICATIONS

- Google Scholar page: https://scholar.google.ca/citations?user=R1gx074AAAAJ
- DBLP page: http://dblp2.uni-trier.de/pers/hd/c/Chui:Carmen

Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceedings (Full Papers)

- [C1] Grüninger, M., Aameri, B., **Chui, C.**, Hahmann, T., Ru, Y., "Foundational Ontologies for Units of Measure". In: Formal Ontology in Information Systems Proceedings of the 10th International Conference, FOIS 2018, Cape Town, South Africa, 19-21 September 2018. Acceptance Rate: 29.2% (14 papers of 48 submissions). **Won Distinguished**Paper Award. 2018, pp. 211–224. URL: https://doi.org/10.3233/978-1-61499-910-2-211.
- [C2] **Chui, C.**, Grüninger, M., "A Molecular Structure Ontology for Medicinal Chemistry". In: Formal Ontology in Information Systems Proceedings of the 9th International Conference, FOIS 2016, Annecy, France, July 6-9, 2016. Acceptance Rate: 30.9% (25 papers of 80 submissions). 2016, pp. 285–298. URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.3233/978-1-61499-660-6-285.
- [C3] **Chui, C.**, Grüninger, M., "Mathematical Foundations for Participation Ontologies". In: Formal Ontology in Information Systems Proceedings of the Eighth International Conference, FOIS 2014, September, 22-25, 2014, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Acceptance Rate: 29.6% (24 papers of 81 submissions). 2014, pp. 105-118. URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.3233/978-1-61499-438-1-105.
- [C4] Chui, C., Grüninger, M., "Merging the DOLCE and PSL Upper Ontologies". In: KEOD 2014 Proceedings of the International Conference on Knowledge Engineering and Ontology Development, Rome, Italy, 21-24 October, 2014. Acceptance Rate: 18% (78 submissions). An updated and revised version of this paper appears in [B1]. Nominated for Best Student Paper Award. SciTePress, 2014, pp. 16-26. ISBN: 978-989-758-049-9. URL: https://doi.org/10.5220/0005027100160026.
- [C5] Grüninger, M., Hahmann, T., Katsumi, M., **Chui, C.**, "A Sideways Look at Upper Ontologies". In: Formal Ontology in Information Systems Proceedings of the Eighth International Conference, FOIS 2014, September, 22-25, 2014, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Acceptance Rate: 29.6% (24 papers of 81 submissions). 2014, pp. 9-22. URL: https://doi.org/10.3233/978-1-61499-438-1-9.

Peer-Reviewed Workshop Proceedings (Full Papers)

- [W1] **Chui, C.**, Grüninger, M., "Verification and Modularization of the DOLCE Upper Ontology". In: Proceedings of the Joint Ontology Workshops 2017 Episode 3: The Tyrolean Autumn of Ontology, Bozen-Bolzano, Italy, September 21-23, 2017. Sept. 2017. URL: http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2050/FOUST paper 1.pdf.
- [W2] Grüninger, M., Chui, C., Katsumi, M., "Upper Ontologies in COLORE". In: Proceedings of the Joint Ontology Workshops 2017 Episode 3: The Tyrolean Autumn of Ontology, Bozen-Bolzano, Italy, September 21-23, 2017. Sept. 2017. URL: http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2050/FOUST_paper_2.pdf.

- [W3] Aameri, B., Grüninger, M., **Chui, C.**, "Anti-Modules". In: Proceedings of the Joint Ontology Workshops 2016 Episode 2: The French Summer of Ontology co-located with the 9th International Conference on Formal Ontology in Information Systems (FOIS 2016). Annecy, France, July 2016. URL: http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-1660/womocoe-paper2.pdf.
- [W4] **Chui, C.**, Grüninger, M., van Berkel, M., "Ontology Mapping in an e-Commerce Application". In: Formal Ontologies Meet Industry 7th International Workshop, FOMI 2015, Berlin, Germany, August 5, 2015, Proceedings. Acceptance Rate: 61.1% (11 papers of 18 submissions). 2015, pp. 25–38. URL: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-21545-7 3.

Book Chapters

[B1] **Chui, C.**, Grüninger, M., "Techniques for Merging Upper Ontologies". In: Knowledge Discovery, Knowledge Engineering and Knowledge Management - 6th International Joint Conference, IC3K 2014, Rome, Italy, October 21-24, 2014, Revised Selected Papers. 2014, pp. 273-292. URL: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-25840-9_18.

Prepared Manuscripts

[M1] **Chui, C.**, Grüninger, M., "Drug Discovery as Model Construction". To be submitted to the Journal of Cheminformatics.

Scholarly Presentations & Talks

- [S1] An Ontological Approach to Medicinal Chemistry. Presented to The Lautens Research Group in the Department of Chemistry at the University of Toronto. July 2017.
- [S2] A Molecular Structure Ontology for Medicinal Chemistry. Presented [C2] at the Formal Ontology in Information Systems (FOIS 2016) in Annecy, France. July 2016.
- [S3] Anti-Modules. Presented [W3] at the Proceedings of the Joint Ontology Workshops (JOWO 2016). July 2016.
- [S4] Merging the DOLCE and PSL Upper Ontologies. Presented [C4] at the Proceedings of the International Conference on Knowledge Engineering and Ontology Development (KEOD 2014). Oct. 2014.
- [S5] Breaking Down DOLCE: Overview of the Verification of the DOLCE Ontology. Presented at the Toronto Ontology Festival (TOFFEE). Aug. 2012.
- [S6] Overview of Current Research Projects. Presented at the Toronto Semantic Web Meetup Group: What's Happening in the Semantic Technologies Lab? Event. Oct. 2012.
- [S7] Reasoning with Ontology Mappings. Presented at the MIE Scientific Writing Course (run by Debby Repka). July 2012.

TEACHING AND MENTORING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

09/2011-present

University of Toronto

♀ Toronto, Canada

In addition to invigilating faculty-wide exams, I designed and conducted tutorials, held office hours, graded progress and final reports, and designed programming labs and quizzes, and graded assignments, tests, and exams.

At the undergraduate level:

- MIE191: Introduction to Mechanical and Industrial Engineering
- Winter 2015-2017

- Taught by Professor Pierre Sullivan
- MIE350: Design & Analysis of Information Systems

Fall 2011-2017

- Taught by Professors Reza Samavi (Fall 2011) and Michael Grüninger (Fall 2012 onwards)
- MIE457: Knowledge Modelling & Management

Winter 2015-2018

• Taught by Professor Michael Grüninger

At the *graduate* level:

• MIE1505: Enterprise Modelling

Fall 2016

Taught by Professor Michael Grüninger

Client/Student Mentor

01/2017-04/2017

University of Toronto

♀ Toronto, Canada

As part of the APS 1203/1204 course offered with the Prospective Professors in Training (PPIT) program, I was a mentor for a group of six first-year undergraduate students taking their Engineering Strategies & Practice II (APS 112) course. The group's project is to redesign mathematics in the classroom to make the subject more engaging and interesting for high-school students. We have been featured in the UofT Engineering News in the following article: http://news.engineering.utoronto.ca/engineering-educational-experience/.

RESEARCH AND INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant

09/2011-present

Semantic Technologies Lab, University of Toronto

♀ Toronto, Canada

- Help specify the metadata and formalize logical methods to relate ontologies to one another within the COmmon Logic Ontology REpository (COLORE) project
- Assisted with *local* International Association for Ontology & Its Application (IAOA) events:
 - IAOA Summer Institute on Upper Ontologies 2017
 - Toronto Ontology Festival (TOFFEE) 2012

Database Analyst

05/2010-08/2010

Mercer (Canada) Ltd.

♀ Toronto, Canada

Web Application Support Specialist, Database Analyst

05/2009-08/2009

Mercer (Canada) Ltd.

♀ Toronto, Canada

Web Application Support Specialist

Mercer (Canada) Ltd.

Student Intern (Cell Culture of Myometrial Cells)

06/2006-08/2006

Lunenfeld-Tanenbaum Research Institute, Mount Sinai Hospital

? Toronto, Canada

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming & Markup Languages CSS, HTML, Java, JavaScript, PHP, Python, SQL, T_FX, Visual Basic, XHTML, and XML.

Knowledge Modelling/Representation Languages BPMN, Common Logic, Description Logic, First-Order Logic, IDEF, OWL, Petri Nets, Prolog, Prover9, RDF/S, Simul8, SPARQL, SWRL, and UML.

Computer Applications Adobe Creative Suite (Illustrator, Photoshop), Eclipse, Intalio BPMS, ŁTEX, MATLAB, Microsoft Office (Access, Excel, PowerPoint, Project, Visio, & Word), Microsoft SQL Server, Minitab, Prolog, Protégé, Prover9-Mace4, and Vampire.

Operating Systems Macintosh OS X, Linux, Microsoft Windows.

AWARDS AND HONOURS

Distinguished Paper Award at FOIS 2018 for [C1]	September 2018
Nominated for Best Student Paper award at KEOD 2014 for [C4]	October 2014
Mechanical And Industrial Engineering Admission Scholarship (\$1,000)	2007
Faculty Of Applied Science And Engineering Admission Scholarship (\$1,000)	2007

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES & ASSOCIATIONS

International Association for Ontology & Its Applications (IAOA)	2011-present
ONTOLOG Forum	2011-present
Ontario Society of Professional Engineers (OSPE)	2011-present
Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)	2011-present
Institute of Industrial Engineers (IIE)	2011-present

PERSONAL

English (native), French (limited working proficiency) Languages

Citizenship Canadian